# **Manita Choudhary**

GIS Professional Status: Canadian PR Driving License: Full G Class



# ABOUT ME

As an experienced Analyst, I am able to responsibly lead, manage and supervise GIS and LiDAR projects. I have gained the expertise to teach, assist, manage and organize different Geography and GIS courses along with a culmination of academic prowess.

I enjoy implementing LEAN (Six Sigma) methodologies for process improvement. A quick learner, team player, quality-oriented with management, leadership, and problem-solving skills.

# CERTIFICATION

#### **CARTOGRAPHY**

ESRI, 2021

# LEAN GREEN BELT (Six Sigma)

QCDMS Consultants, 2020

# **EXPERTISE**

# **PROGRAMMING SKILLS**

C, C++, C#, R Script, Visual Basics, Java, SQL, JavaScript, VB Script, HTML, Python.

#### APPLICATION/TOOLS

RiPROCESS, POSPac, ArcGIS Pro, ArcGIS Hub, FME, R Studio, MapInfo, ENVY, Visual Studio, Adobe Contribute, Google Earth, Google SketchUp, Matlab, SPSS, GeoProMT, Microsoft Office, AutoCAD, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Premiere Pro CS5.5.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Lidar and Photography Analyst

Fugro Canada | Toronto | Jan 2020 - Sept 2020

- Supported Fugro's Asset Management team by leading and supervising all LiDAR projects
- Provided geospatial production management support, data processing, data analysis, problem-solving and task management
- Daily production oversight and reporting for all geospatial related projects using LEAN methodologies (KanBan, Kaizen, KPI etc.)
- Ensured data quality is optimal by applying QA/QC principles for both LiDAR and Photogrammetry projects
- In charge of creating Standard Operating Procedure (SOP), training videos and documents as part of knowledge sharing

# FUGRO PROJECTS

# **LiDAR Projects**

- Utilized POSPac for Post-processing of trajectory of LiDAR data and then employed RiPROCESS to process, analyze, manage, and visualize mobile laser scanning data (MLS)
- Transformed raw MLS data to widely used, geo-referenced LAS format for further analysis
- Projects: Sugarland (Texas, USA), Virginia (USA), Houston, etc.

#### **Photogrammetry Projects**

- Performed Photogrammetry analysis to extract different assets to support government transportation departments and private entities in condition monitoring, identification of deficiencies and enabling prioritization of roadwork
- QA/QC the asset extraction process and output to maintain the high grade of the product
- Projects: Arizona, Abu Dhabi (UAE), Alaska, Colorado, Dallas, Kansas City, Richardson, Toronto, etc.

### ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

# Adjunct Instructor - Maps: Earth from Above

State University of New York | Buffalo | Spring 2019

 Taught the course and developed course materials such as lectures, presentations, readings, assembled course books, exercises and learning modules, projects and exams

# Senator - Department of Geography

State University of New York | Buffalo | Fall 2018 - Spring 2019

- Reported the proceedings of the meetings to the committee and discussed the next plan of operation
- Voted for additional funding requirements of any department
- Proposed amendments by petition whenever required

#### Course Assistant - Web based GIS

State University of New York | Buffalo | Fall 2016

 Developed course materials such as lectures, presentations (using R markdown), and readings, exercises, learning modules and assembled course books

# Teaching Assistant - Earth Science and Systems II

State University of New York | Buffalo | Spring 2015, 2016, Fall 2015

Organized and taught the Lab component of the Earth Science and Systems II course

# Graduate Assistant - GIAL Lab Attendant

State University of New York | Buffalo | Fall 2012, 2014, Spring 2013

Invited speakers, managed workshops for students in the Department of Geography, assisted students in the GIS lab, etc.

# **Manita Choudhary**

GIS Professional status: Canadian PR Driving License: Full G Class



### **KEY SKILLS**

LiDAR, GIS, Cartography, Coastal Geomorphology, Geoprocessing, Course Coordinator, Curriculum Development, Research, Problem Solving, Team player, Public Speaking, Project Management, Leadership, Process Improvement.

# **EDUCATION**

#### Masters of Science in GIS

State University of New York at Buffalo 2017-2019

# Masters of Arts in Geography

Major - GIS, Coastal Geomorphology University of Mumbai 2010-2012

# Bachelor of Arts in Geography

University of Mumbai 2006-2009

# Bachelor of Computer Applications

Major - Advanced Java University of Mumbai 2006-2009

#### CHECK OUT LINKS

#### LinkedIn

GitHub GeoPortfolio

Rate My Professor

Story Maps Portfolio

# ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE (Continued)

# Lecturer - Earth Science and Systems I

State University of New York | Buffalo | Summer 2013, 2014

Organized and taught the course of Earth Science and Systems

# Teaching Assistant - Earth Science and Systems I

State University of New York | Buffalo | Spring 2014

- Assisted the professor to give students additional attention and instruction
- Taught and supervised the class when the professor was on leave

#### Graduate Assistant - Administration Office

State University of New York | Buffalo | Spring 2013

- Maintained Geography Department website using Adobe Contribute
- Helped professors set up or update their websites

# Teaching Assistant - Web-based GIS

State University of New York | Buffalo | Fall 2012

Organized and taught the lab component of Web-based GIS course

#### ACADEMIC PROJECTS

# Estimating optimal spatial location for Offshore Wind farms using Spatio-Temporal Kriging Teaching Assistant - Web-based GIS

- Calculated the distribution of wind over time and space in Long Island (New York) to estimate optimal spatial locations for offshore wind farms
- Spatio-Temporal (ST) Kriging in R script was utilized to find the potential wind energy source locations

# Suitability Assessment for the habitat of Blanding's Turtle in the Western part of Erie County

- Applied logistic regression model with sightings of turtle, land cover, elevation, proximity to water bodies & transportation networks
- Coefficients were derived using SPSS and ArcGIS was used for the rest of the suitability analysis

# Relative comparison of rill network evolution in two similar soil-mantled experimental landscape

 Hydrologic analysis on Digital Elevation Models (DEMs) derived from experimental landscapes, which were simulated with artificial rainfall and downstream decrement of elevation

# Renderer Menu Tool - Created an ArcGIS Menu using C# which allows to change the rendering of LAS datasets with selection buttons:

- Performed 3D analysis which was backed by photogrammetric analysis with the methodology based on identifying photographic, cartographic and photogrammetric evidence regarding the coastal topographic change
- This identification involved data acquisition, preprocessing, importation in ArcGIS, reclassification (if needed), data analysis, and finally, Spatio-temporal analysis and visualization

# Monitoring Spatio-Temporal Coastal changes: Using LiDAR Data

- Default Fill Symbol Changes the shapefile to one color
- Class Breaks Renderer Changes the shapefile color using class breaks
- Unique Value Renderer Changes the shapefile color using a unique value

# Integrated Coastal Zone Management: Ice Jams

- A detailed report of deterministic decision making based on cost-benefit analysis and standard engineering approach of some stakeholders
- Devised a simplified version of the Watershed Planning Process from CATTARAUGUS CREEK WATERSHED RESOURCE GUIDE